<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.2" packageId="knb-lter-nes.8.1" xsi:schemaLocation="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0  https://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.2.0/xsd/eml.xsd" system="edi">
  <access authSystem="https://pasta.edirepository.org/authentication" order="allowFirst" scope="document">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=NES,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset id="dataset">
    <title>Size-fractionated chlorophyll from water column bottle samples collected during NES-LTER Transect cruises, ongoing since 2017.</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Heidi</givenName>
        <givenName>M</givenName>
        <surName>Sosik</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Northeast U.S. Shelf LTER</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>hsosik@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4591-2842</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Tatiana</givenName>
        <surName>Rynearson</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Northeast U.S. Shelf LTER</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>rynearson@uri.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2951-0066</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Susanne</givenName>
        <surName>Menden-Deuer</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Northeast U.S. Shelf LTER</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>smenden@uri.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8434-4251</userId>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <surName>Ocean Observatories Initiative</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Ocean Observatories Initiative</organizationName>
    </creator>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Pierre</givenName>
        <surName>Marrec</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Northeast U.S. Shelf LTER</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>pmarrec@uri.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7811-4150</userId>
      <role>Postdoctoralresearcher</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>E. Taylor</givenName>
        <surName>Crockford</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Northeast U.S. Shelf LTER</organizationName>
      <role>Technician</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Jaxine</givenName>
        <givenName>L</givenName>
        <surName>Wolfe</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Northeast U.S. Shelf LTER</organizationName>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9620-5382</userId>
      <role>Metadataprovider</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <associatedParty>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Kate</givenName>
        <surName>Morkeski</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>Northeast U.S. Shelf LTER</organizationName>
      <role>Metadataprovider</role>
    </associatedParty>
    <pubDate>2021-04-30</pubDate>
    <abstract>
      <para>Size-fractionated chlorophyll a and phaeopigments are measured from water column bottle samples taken on Northeast U.S. Shelf Long-Term Ecological Research (NES-LTER) Transect cruises (ongoing since 2017), as a proxy for phytoplankton biomass. Sampling frequency is approximately seasonal. Samples were processed by three lab groups using different methods. Four size fractions are included in addition to whole seawater (&gt;0.7 micron): &gt;5 , &lt;10, &gt;10, and &gt;20 microns. These pigments are analyzed using a fluorometer in which fluorescence is measured versus a blank and a standard, and final concentrations are calculated in micrograms per liter (or mg per cubic meter). Some of the data are from cruises in collaboration with the Ocean Observatories Initiative (OOI).</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>Populations</keyword>
      <keyword>Primary production</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER Core Research Areas</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>chlorophyll a</keyword>
      <keyword>marine</keyword>
      <keyword>oceanography</keyword>
      <keyword>phytoplankton</keyword>
      <keyword>seawater</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>CHLOROPHYLL</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>NASA GCMD</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>CHLOROPHYLL</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>NOAA NODC Data Types Thesaurus</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>This data package is released to the "public domain" under Creative Commons CC0 1.0 "No Rights Reserved" (see: https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). It is considered professional etiquette to provide attribution of the original work if this data package is shared in whole or by individual components. A generic citation is provided for this data package on the website https://portal.edirepository.org (herein "website") in the summary metadata page. Communication (and collaboration) with the creators of this data package is recommended to prevent duplicate research or publication. This data package (and its components) is made available "as is" and with no warranty of accuracy or fitness for use. The creators of this data package and the website shall not be liable for any damages resulting from misinterpretation or misuse of the data package or its components. For those data identified in the data table from the Ocean Observatories Initiative (OOI), see the Limitation of Liability and Disclaimer in the OOI User Terms and Conditions (https://oceanobservatories.org/how-to-use-and-cite-data/). Periodic updates of this data package may be available from the website. Thank you.&#13;
</para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>NES-LTER Transect</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-71.068</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-70.5227</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>41.3246</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>39.7576</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates/>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <annotation>
      <propertyURI label="is about">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/IAO_0000136</propertyURI>
      <valueURI label="Chlorophyll pigment concentrations in water bodies">http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P02/current/CPWC/</valueURI>
    </annotation>
    <maintenance>
      <description>ongoing</description>
    </maintenance>
    <contact>
      <organizationName>Northeast U.S. Shelf LTER</organizationName>
      <positionName>Nes-Lter Information Manager</positionName>
      <electronicMailAddress>lter-nes-info@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>Three lab groups led by PIs Sosik, Rynearson, and Menden-Deuer provide size-fractionated chlorophyll data from CTD Rosette Bottle and Bucket Sampling on NES-LTER cruises. Methods specific to each lab group are distinguished in each section of methods below.&#13;
The Sosik lab methods are used for the data that we are including from the Ocean Observatories Initiative (OOI).</para>
          <para># CTD Rosette Bottle and Bucket Sampling on NES-LTER cruises</para>
          <para>Sosik: Samples were collected from the water column at multiple depths using Niskin bottles on a CTD rosette system. At surface locations and at additional depths at high-priority stations, samples were collected for both &lt;10 micron and whole seawater size fractions, with &lt;10 micron sampling at depth targeted to the chl max and another depth with detectable CTD fluorescence. At the remaining locations, samples were not size-fractioned. For each sample, two to three duplicate bottles were filled from each Niskin and were stored in a cooler until filtered on-ship. Some samples were collected at the surface with a bucket.</para>
          <para>Rynearson: Samples were collected from the water column at multiple depths using Niskin bottles on a CTD rosette system. Samples were collected from all LTER stations with a total of 12 samples per station comprised of 2 size fractions (&gt;5 and &gt;20 micron) from each of 3 (sometimes 4) depths: surface, chl max, below max (or other). For each depth, two bottles were filled with seawater and returned to the ship's lab for filtering. &#13;
On cruise EN608 only: Samples were collected from 4-8 depths from each LTER station. Each Niskin sampled was used to fill duplicate sample bottles for whole seawater and for smaller size fractions, which varied by station, were focused on surface, subsurface chlorophyll max (SCM), and below SCM, and included  &gt;5 microns and &gt;20 microns. Samples were kept in a cooler until filtered. </para>
          <para>Menden-Deuer: The Menden-Deuer group conducts incubation experiments; chlorophyll is provided here only for the starting point (time zero). At each depth, 2-4 Niskins were filled and their seawater transferred to a 10-L polycarbonate carboy through a 200 micron mesh prefilter. Triplicate 120-150 mL subsamples were collected from the carboys for each of the size fractions, which included &gt;20, &gt;10, &gt;5, and &gt;0 microns for cruises EN608, EN617, and EN627; since cruise EN644 only the &gt;10 and &gt;0 microns. The suite of size fractions measured varied acrcoss cruises and stations.</para>
          <para>#  Chlorophyll Filtering Protocol</para>
          <para>Sosik: For each sample, a known volume was poured through a GF/F filter under low vacuum suction (5-10 in. Hg). The &lt;10 micron size fraction was separated using a filter funnel containing a 10 micron Nitex mesh screen above the GF/F. Filters were transferred to tissue capsules and frozen in liquid nitrogen until being extracted. Sosik lab group usually has 2 replicates from the same niskin bottle, indicated by a or b in the data table.</para>
          <para>Rynearson: Size fractionation was accomplished by pouring one bottle from each depth through a 5 micron Sterlitech polycarbonate filter and one through a 20 micron Sterlitech polycarbonate filter under low vacuum suction. Filters were transferred to 5 mL cryogenic vials and flash-frozen in liquid nitrogen until being extracted. Rynearson lab group usually has 2 replicates from the same niskin bottle, indicated by a or b in the data table.&#13;
On cruise EN608 only: Samples were filtered by homogenizing a 1-L bottle and pouring 200 mL through each of a 5 micron polycarbonate filter and a 20 micron polycarbonate filter with vacuum &lt;20 kpa. Each filter was transferred to a tube containing 6 mL of 90% acetone previously chilled to -20 C, returned to -20 C, and extracted 20-30 hours later.</para>
          <para>Menden-Deuer: Size fractionation was accomplished by pouring each sample through a GF/F (nominal 0.7 micron pore size) or 25-mm 5um (Poretics Polyester GVS Life Sciences), 10um (Isopore PolyCarbonate Millipore), or 20um (Polycarbonate Maine Manufacturing) filter on a manifold with vacuum not exceeding 200 mBar.  Filters were transferred to glass tubes containing 6 mL 95% ethanol at room temperature, which were then stored in darkness at room temperature for 12 h +/-2 h prior to reading on board ship. Menden-Deuer lab group usually has 3 replicates from multiple niskin bottles combined from same depth, indicated by a, b, or c in the data table.</para>
          <para># Laboratory chlorophyll a measurement</para>
          <para>Sosik: Filters were removed from liquid nitrogen storage and transferred to glass test tubes. They were then extracted in 5 mL of 90% acetone for 24 hours on ice in a dark refrigerator. They were then vortexed and centrifuged. The solution was measured on a Turner Designs Handheld Aquafluor fluorometer, acidified with 3 drops of 10% hydrochloric acid, and measured again. If the chlorophyll readings were over the range of the fluorometer, the solution was diluted as needed. A blank and a solid standard were measured at the beginning and end of each batch of samples, and the fluorometer was calibrated approximately annually using a serial dilution of a commercially available stock solution (Sigma-Aldrich). </para>
          <para>Rynearson: Filters were removed from liquid nitrogen storage and extracted in 5 mL of 90% acetone for 24 hours on ice in a dark refrigerator. They were then vortexed, and the solution was measured on a Turner Designs Handheld Aquafluor fluorometer, acidified with 3 drops of 10% hydrochloric acid, and measured again. If the chlorophyll readings were over the range of the fluorometer, the solution was diluted as needed. A blank and a solid standard were measured at the beginning and end of each batch of samples, and the fluorometer was calibrated approximately annually using a serial dilution of a commercially available stock solution (Sigma-Aldrich). &#13;
On cruise EN608 only: Tubes were removed from freezer shortly before processing, vortexed for 10 seconds, and (begining with cast 15) centrifuged for 3 minutes. The supernatant was measured on a Turner Designs 10-AU-005 Benchtop Fluorometer, acidified with 2-3 drops of 10% hydrochloric acid, and measured again. If the chlorophyll readings were over the range of the fluorometer, the solution was diluted as needed. A blank and a solid standard were measured at the beginning and end of each batch of samples.</para>
          <para>Menden-Deuer: In the presence of only red light, each tube was vortexed for 10 seconds, and its solution was then poured into a new tube and measured on a Turner Designs 10-AU-005 Benchtop Fluorometer. Two drops of 10% hydrochloric acid were added to each tube, and it was measured again. If the reading after acidification was the same as the reading before acidification, an additional drop of acid was added. Tubes were measured 30 seconds to one hour after acidification. Before and after each batch of samples, a blank, blank + acid, and a solid standard were measured. </para>
          <para># Data Assembly and Cleaning</para>
          <para>The data table was assembled from three sources: the REST Application Programming Interface (API) of the NES-LTER data system, data sheets provided by the Menden-Deuer lab, and a data sheet from the OOI Alfresco document server. &#13;
Assembly starts in the main R markdown by concatenating cruises called from the NES-LTER REST API for values measured for the Sosik and Rynearson labs, and separately concatenating cruises provided by the Menden-Deuer lab.&#13;
We add CTD bottle metadata (time, latitude, longitude, depth) from the NES-LTER REST API, identify when there are corresponding samples with values measured for multiple lab groups for the same (or paired) cast at same depth, then merge the REST API and Menden-Deuer data.&#13;
In a separate R markdown we join additional cruises from the REST API of the NES-LTER data system with the OOI data sheet to add the identifier for those samples for which OOI is the authoritative data source. Please refer to the R markdown document for the exact version of the EXCEL file accessed via web services from the OOI Alfresco document server for Cruise Data from the Coastal Pioneer Array.&#13;
Then in the main R markdown we add those cruises in collaboration with OOI to the compiled data table.&#13;
For all records, we calculated the distance to the nearest NES-LTER standard station L1 to L13 (standard for cruises starting with EN617 in August 2018).&#13;
The final step in data assembly is the addition of a quality code for the Sosik and Rynearson values that is not yet provided through the REST API.&#13;
Data cleaning included rounding values. Some hard-coding was needed to correct specific records. &#13;
Data assembly, data cleaning and metadata template assembly were performed in R Markdown. Further documentation can be found on GitHub, at https://github.com/WHOIGit/nes-lter-chl-transect.</para>
          <para># Quality Assurance</para>
          <para>We assured that the geographic and temporal coverage of the clean data table were within expected ranges. We provide a column in the data table to indicate the quality of values measured for the Sosik and Rynearson labs. All values provided for the Menden-Deuer lab are considered good quality. We confirm that all values provided for the OOI-funded replicates are equivalent to the data sheet as in the OOI Alfresco. We checked differences between replicates, visually inspected plotted values, and performed a range check.&#13;
</para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>Northeast U.S. Shelf LTER</title>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Heidi</givenName>
          <surName>Sosik</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>hsosik@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4591-2842</userId>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Stace</givenName>
          <surName>Beaulieu</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>sbeaulieu@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2609-5453</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Changsheng</givenName>
          <surName>Chen</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>c1chen@umassd.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8715-6101</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Rubao</givenName>
          <surName>Ji</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>rji@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8839-5427</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Steven</givenName>
          <surName>Lentz</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>slentz@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7498-0281</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Joel</givenName>
          <surName>Llopiz</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>jllopiz@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-7584-7471</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Susanne</givenName>
          <surName>Menden-Deuer</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>smenden@uri.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8434-4251</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Michael</givenName>
          <surName>Neubert</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>mneubert@whoi.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-8820-5008</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Tatiana</givenName>
          <surName>Rynearson</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>rynearson@uri.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-2951-0066</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <givenName>Rachel</givenName>
          <surName>Stanley</surName>
        </individualName>
        <electronicMailAddress>rstanle2@wellesley.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-4860-2476</userId>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <abstract>
        <para>The Northeast U.S. Shelf (NES) Long-Term Ecological Research (LTER) project integrates observations, experiments, and models to understand and predict how planktonic food webs are changing, and how those changes impact the productivity of higher trophic levels. The NES-LTER is co-located with the Northeast U.S. Continental Shelf Large Marine Ecosystem, spanning the Middle Atlantic Bight and Gulf of Maine. Our focal cross-shelf transect extends about 150 km southward from Martha’s Vineyard, MA, to just beyond the shelf break. Our overarching question is: How is climate change impacting the pelagic NES ecosystem and, in particular, affecting the relationship between compositional (e.g., species diversity and size structure) and aggregate (e.g., rates of primary production, and transfer of energy to important forage fish species) variability?</para>
      </abstract>
      <funding>
        <para>NSF Award OCE-1655686</para>
      </funding>
      <relatedProject>
        <title>Ocean Observatories Initiative</title>
        <funding>NSF Award OCE-1743430</funding>
      </relatedProject>
    </project>
  </dataset>
  <annotations>
    <annotation references="dataset">
      <propertyURI label="is about">http://purl.obolibrary.org/obo/IAO_0000136</propertyURI>
      <valueURI label="Chlorophyll pigment concentrations in water bodies">http://vocab.nerc.ac.uk/collection/P02/current/CPWC/</valueURI>
    </annotation>
  </annotations>
</eml:eml>
